Guide to the Ambrose Bierce Papers, 1872-1913
Department of Special Collections
Ambrose Bierce Papers,
1872-1913
Special Collections M080
Bierce, Ambrose, 1842-1914?
2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Purchase 1942 and 1974; gift of Stanford Library Association, 1949.
BIOGRAPHY
Ambrose Gwinett Bierce was born in Meigs County, Ohio on June 24, 1842, the son of Marcus Aurelius and Laura Sherwood Bierce. Little is known of his childhood; he became a printer's apprentice in Kosciusko County, Indiana, before entering the Kentucky Military Institute in 1859.
Shortly before entering the Union Army after the outbreak of the Civil War, Bierce was a laborer and waiter in Elkhart, Indiana. In the war, he served with the 9th Regiment of Indiana Volunteers. Bierce progressed in rank from private to lieutenant and became the acting typographical engineer on Gen. W. B. Hazen's staff. At the battle of Kenesaw Mountain, Bierce sustained a near-fatal head wound from which it took months to recover.
Following the war, Bierce became an aid to Treasury Department agents collecting abandoned Southern property. He joined Hazen's surveying expedition to the Far West in 1866 and stayed on in San Francisco working for the U. S. Mint.
In San Francisco Bierce began to pursue his literary interests. In 1868, he succeeded his friend James T. Watkins as the editor of News-Letter. Bierce married Mary Ellen Day on Christmas Day, 1871, and eventually had three children, Day, Leigh, and Helen.
From 1872-74, Bierce was in England writing for Tom Hood's Fun and James Mortimer's Figaro. He returned to San Francisco in September of 1875. He edited several magazines for the next years, including Argonaut and the Wasp; he also wrote his "Prattle" and The Dance of Death.
Bierce became a columnist for the San Francisco Examiner in 1887 but continued to produce his own books and stories. He was sent in 1896 by the Examiner to Washington, D.C. to cover the Railroad Funding Bill controversy. He stayed on in Washington as a political reporter for many years, also publishing his own literary work.
In late 1913, Bierce took a trip through the Southwest into Mexico where he mysteriously disappeared.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The Ambrose Gwinett Bierce Papers consist primarily of correspondence to Bierce from 1872-1913. There are several letters by Bierce himself but of these, many are printed copies or carbons. Several of the photos in the collection have notations and inscriptions in Bierce's hand, as do many of the incoming letters. Correspondents include: Upton Sinclair, Joaquin Miller, Gertrude Atherton, H.L. Mencken, Edwin Markham, William Randolph Hearst, George Sterling, and Percival Pollard.
The papers cover Bierce's journalistic career in England, San Francisco, and Washington, D.C.; the publication of his works (see especially the letters to Bierce from his publisher Walter Neale); and commentaries on the political controversies and governmental policies of the day including the Spanish-American War, the question of annexation, and the treaty of Hawaii. The telegram correspondence to Bierce in 1896 details the Railroad Funding Bill controversy which Bierce covered in Washington, D.C. for William Randolph Hearst's San Francisco Examiner. Other topics include women's suffrage and the Titanic.
The collection also contains reminiscences and memorabilia of the Civil War, including the sketchbook Bierce kept while serving as a Union topographer with the staff of General W. B. Hazen.
Of special note is the diary which records, (probably in his secretary's hand) Bierce's wanderings through the Southwest and into Mexico in late 1913 before his disappearance somewhere in Mexico. Several Bierce biographers have agreed that this diary was probably written by Carrie Christiansen from letters that Bierce sent her while on his journey (see note by Paul Fatout in Bierce collection file, April 1945).
CONTAINER LIST
- SERIES I: CORRESPONDENCE
  - AMBROSE BIERCE, INCOMING & OUTGOING
    arranged alphabetically
    - Abbot, Willis J. Apr 2, 1896, Apr 27, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ainsworth, F.C. Jun 8, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Allen, [?] May 8, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Allen, Charles Dexter Oct 22, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Barr, Robert Mar 2, 1893, Mar 15, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bierce, A[lbert]?S. Jun 3, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Bierce, Ambrose, Outgoing to:
      - Allen, Charles Dexter Sept 27, 1911, Printed copy, 1 page. Army & Navy Club, Washington, D.C. letterhead. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        AB discusses "The Dance of Death." Postscript describes demise of Rulofson and Harcourt.
      - Allen, Charles Dexter Oct 25, 1911, Printed copy, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Again discusses "The Dance of Death." Discusses a Dr. Bowere, tried wife-murder and "the really serious offence of stealing books from a public library." Informs CDA that Walter Neale will contact him about AB's "Collected Works."
      - Bierce, Lora Mar 13, 1911, ALS with envelope, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        AB is sending her a book of "Grand Cañon views."
      - Black, James D. [with print of AB] Nov 1907, ALS with envelope and ink of AB, 3 pages. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Mentions Sterling and AB's dislike of "limited editions." Mentions S.O. Howes. Thanks Black for "Foregoing your wish to republish the London books. They are trash."
      - Morrow, W.C. Apr 10, 1910, ALS with envelope, 2 pages. (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Speaks of hoping to visit Morrow and wife and perhaps the Panama Canal. Never cared much for San Francisco. Hopes to spend the summer with his "hermit brother."
      - Neale, Walter Feb 15, 1912, Carbon of TLS, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Discusses firm of Chatto & Windus and respective rights to AB stories.
      - Neale, Walter Feb 16, 1912, Carbon of TLS, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Syndication of stories and AB's 40% royalty.
      - Neale, Walter Mar 6, 1912, ALS, 4 pages. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Letter-writing and form rejection slips. Neale is right in not replying to an objectionable letter for "in most matters, as in war, it is a good rule to do what the enemy least expects." Discusses Civil War battle of Chickamauga. AB is at work on "Little Johnny." Incomplete postscript "It is awfully good of you to..."
      - Newbegin, Mr. Oct 11, 1911, Carbon copy of TLS, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Prompts Newbegin to pay his bill. AB handwriting on verso.
      - Newbegin, Mr. Oct 13, 1911, Carbon copy of TLS, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Date in AB's hand. Accepts Newbegin's offer. Hopes Neale and Newbegin "will both be good henceforth." AB's hand on verso.
      - Newbegin, Mr. Nov 18, 1911, ALS, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Informs Newbegin that a letter to him from Bierce may have been addressed incorrectly.
      - Pollard, Percival Apr 22, 1893, Typewritten copy, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Writes of Pollard's work. Thanks PP for Figaro. AB is sorry to miss Harte [Walter Blackburn Harte]. Mentions Robert Barr and Gladstone. New London newspaper enthusiasm for The Fiend's Delight. E.W. Townsend's address typed on verso.
      - Pollard, Percival Oct 9, 1895, Typed copy, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        AB recovering from a bicycle accident. Mentions visit of Charles Edwin Markham who "has had three months of illness and looks like the devil."
      - Pollard, Percival Oct 12, 1897, Typed copy, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Thanks PP for speaking to the "town Topicist." Examiner unwilling to let AB go. Prattle is dead. Introduces Pollard to Ned Townsend. Postscript: AB has forgotten Townsend's address.
      - Robertson, Ruth Nov 3, 1912, Printed copy, I page. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        AB had visited daughter in Bloomington, Illinois. Will not return again to California. Mentions Bernard Shaw. Advises RR to study English at Berkeley. Asks if RR's father has sold the Livermore sanitarium.
      - Robertson, Ruth Apr 21, 1913, Printed copy, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        AB has sent RR a school book. Mentions Morrow and the difficulty in writing an acceptable play. Postscript: AB wants to see RR's new story.
      - Townsend, E.W. Oct 12, 1897, Typed copy, 1 page. (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Introduces Pollard.
      - [Bierce], Amy, Jun 3 1896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - [Bierce], "The Children", Jun 3 1896 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - [Bierce], Helen (See also Helen Cowden) (Box 1, Folder 3)
        - Aug 24 1909
        - Sep 2 1907
        - Sep 7 1907
      - [Bierce, Helen] "Bit", Jun 23 1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - [HB and Hary Cowden] "Bit & Harry", Jun 23 1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Bierce, Leigh (Box 1, Folder 3)
        - Feb ? 1896
        - May 13 1896
        - Mar 29 1899
      - Block, Rudolph (Box 1, Folder 3)
        - Jun 19 1900
        - Sep 30 1903
        - Aug 15 1904, (AB's hand on verso)
      - Bull, Lucy C. (sec'y to E.C. Stedman), Apr 22 1899, (Stedman's hand on verso) (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Carpenter, Grant, May 16 1913 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - C[arrinton], C[arroll] (Box 1, Folder 3)
        - Oct 19 1897, (transcription)
        - Jan 7 1898, (transcription)
        - Sep 26 1898, (transcription)
        - Mar 9 1899
        - nd, (transcription)
      - Carson, Will, May 9 1893 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Chamberlain, S.S. (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Nov 1 1895
        - Feb 1 1896
        - Feb 20 1896
        - Apr 24 1896
        - Jun 10 1896
        - Jan 10 1907
        - Aug 30 1907
        - Sep 27 1907
        - Oct 7 1907, (AB's hand on verso)
        - Mar 17 1908, (AB's hand on verso)
        - nd
      - Chatto, Andrew (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Sep 13 1873
        - Sep 25 1891
        - Nov 5 1891
        - Jan 21 1892
      - Combined Press, The, Dec 2 1895 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - [Cowden], Harry, Jun 28 1907 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "H & H" [Helen and Harry Cowden], Jun 28 1907 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Cowley-Brown, John (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Nov 16 1899
        - Dec 27 1899
        - Sept 15 1905
        - Dec 7 1906
        - Mar 26 1907
        - Mar 30 1907
        - Feb 15 [1910]
        - Jan 13 1912
      - Curtis, Geo[rge], Byron (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Jul 22 1872
        - Apr 13 1874
        - May 8 1874
        - Aug 22 1874
        - Sept 19 1874
        - Sept 23 1874
        - Oct 19 1874
        - Jul 8 1875
      - Davis, Sam (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - [?] 24 1892
        - Nov 13 [1909]
        - May 18 [1913]
      - Examiner, The (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Feb 1 1896
        - Feb 2 1896
        - Mar [?] 1896
        - Mar 2 [1896]
        - Mar 22 1896
        - Apr 4 1896
        - Apr 23 1896
        - May 6 1896
        - May 6 [1896]
        - May 8 1896
        - May 19 1896
      - Flecker, James Elroy, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Francillon, R.E. (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Mar 19 1875
        - Apr 11 1875
        - Apr 18 [1875]
      - Fuller, Margaret [sec'y to E.C. Stedman], Dec 26 1901 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Garnett, Porter (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Aug 12 1910
        - May 9 1912
      - Gowing, Richard (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Mar 4 1875
        - Mar 11 1875
        - Mar 12 1875
        - Apr 28 1875
        - May 3 1875
      - Hamilton, Ed (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Feb [20?] 1896
        - Mar 2 1896
        - Mar 2 1896
        - Mar 15 1896
        - Mar 18 1896
        - Mar 31 1896
        - Mar 31 [1896]
        - Apr [?] 1896
        - Apr 5 1896
        - Apr 7 1896
        - Apr 21 1896
      - Harte, W[alter] B[lackburn] (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Feb 17 1892
        - Apr 28 1892
        - Jun 9 1892
      - Harte, W[alter] B[lackburn] (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Aug 17 1892
        - Sept 17 1892
        - Sept 27 1892
        - Oct 21 1892
        - Oct 25 1892
      - Havens, Lila R., May 27 [1912] (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Hawes, Alex G., Apr 20 1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Hawley, May N. (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - May 16 1880
        - [?] [1880]
      - Hawley, H.W., May 5 1896 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Hawson, Florence, Jan 30 1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Haxton, H.R., [?] 1888 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Hazen, Jean (sec'y to Edwin Markham), Feb 14 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Hecht, Hilda A., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Henderson, A.B., Nov 7 1892 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Higbee, D., May 6 1892 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Houghton, S. [C?], Sept 8 1902 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Howes, S.O. (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Jul 7 1905
        - Nov 15 1906
        - May 5 1907
        - Sept 13 1907
        - Oct 17 1907
        - May 8 1911
        - Jun 21 1911
      - Hughes, Edgar, Sept 7 1875 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Humphrey, C.F., Nov 24 1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Humphreys, [M?]. G., Jul 25 1891 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Ihmsen, M.F. (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Aug 20 1904
        - Aug 26 1904
        - Dec 13 1905, [AB's hand on verso]
        - Jul 9 1907
      - Kelly, Allen P., Jan 6 1885 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Kenward, [Henry], Nov 20 1874 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Knox, Thos. W., Jul 25 1875 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - LaGrange, 0[scar] H. (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Jan 27 1872
        - Jul 17 1884
        - Feb 3 1902
        - Mar 29 1902
        - May 15 1902
        - Jun 24 1902
        - Jul 20 1902
        - Sept 4 1902
        - [Oct 11] [1902]
        - Oct 11 1902
        - Oct 24 1902
      - Lane, Anne W., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Langton, Wm. M., Dec 18 1892 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Lawrence, [Andrew Middleton] (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Apr 8 1896
        - Apr 24 1896
        - Apr 26 1896
        - May 1 1896
        - May 1 1896
        - May 12 1896
        - May 13 1896
        - May 22 1896
        - [?] 1896
      - Lee, Henry (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Jul 7 1872
        - Dec 19 1874
        - Dec 24 1874
      - Loveman, Samuel (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Oct 20 1908
        - Mar 15 1909
        - May 18 1909
        - Jun 24 1909
        - [Jul 27] [1909]
        - Nov 4 1909
        - [Dec 23] [1909]
        - [Mar 7] [1910]
        - May 20 1911
        - Dec 11 1911
        - poems, 2 pages n.d.
      - Lyster, Fred, [ca. March] [1875] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Macfarlane, E.C. (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - [August] [1884?]
        - Aug 26 1884
        - Sept 20 1884
        - Sept 23 1884
        - Oct 27 1884
        - Oct [?] 1884
        - Nov 20 1884
        - [Nov 21] [1884]
        - [Nov 22] [1884]
        - [Nov 23] [1884]
        - Nov 30 1884
        - Dec 9 1884
        - Dec 11 1884
        - Feb 22 1886
        - June 6 1886
        - Mar 10 1889
      - MacKay, Robert (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Apr 18 1903
        - Aug 18 1906
      - Markham, Anna C., Dec 30 1898, [with transcription] (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Markham, Edwin, Dec 24 1898 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Maxim, Hudson, Nov 25 1910 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - McCrackin, Josephine (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Nov 14 1897, [transcription]
        - Dec 30 1897, [transcription]
        - Jan 30 1900
        - May 21 1900
        - Sept 10 1900
        - Feb 16 1913
        - May 25 1913
        - July 21 1913
        - Sept 16 1913
        - n.d.
      - McEwen, Arthur, Apr 21 [l892] (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Mencken, H.L. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Apr 22 [1913?]
        - Apr 26 [1913?]
        - May 2 [1913?]
        - May 18 [1913?]
      - Merrill, George B., Feb 4 1892 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Millard, Bailey (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - May 29 1905
        - Nov 8 1905
        - Jan 31 1906
        - May 9 1906
        - May 22 1906
        - n.d.
      - Miller, O.C. (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - July 10 1879
        - Aug 6 1879
        - Aug 16 1879
      - Miller, Joaquin, [ca Apr 5][1875] (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Mitchell, Alex L., Dec 13 [19]03
      - Moffett, S.E., May 5 1896 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - [Mork?], Rudolph, [1903?] (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Mortimer, James (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Apr 14 1874
        - Apr 16 1874
        - Apr 17 1874
        - [ca June 15] [1874]
        - [ca June 23] [1874]
        - July 11 1874
        - July 13 1874
        - Oct 1 1874
        - Oct 25 1874
        - Nov 13 1874
        - Nov 22 1874
        - Dec 18 1874
        - Jan 6 1875, [with photo of JM]
        - Jan 15 [1875], [fragment]
        - Jan 16 [1875]
        - Jan 18 1875
        - Jan 23 1875
        - Feb 3 1875
        - Apr 17 1875
      - Moss, H.A., May 26 1914 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Neale, H.S., July 1 1911 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Neale, Walter Jr., Dec 13 1909 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Neale, Walter [AB's publisher]
        - Dec 13 1905-June 27 1913 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
        - Dec 13 1905-June 27 1913 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Newmann, Paul, Oct 1 1885 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Norcross Chas. P. (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - July 24 1908
        - Aug 4 1908, [AB's hand on front]
        - Dec 7 1908, [AB's hand on front]
        - Mar 16 1909
        - Mar 19 1909
      - Palmer, C.M. (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Feb 3 1896
        - June 9 1896
      - Partridge, Ned, [March] [1892] (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Pausill, Mrs., Oct 19 [1895] (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Phelan, James D., Aug 17 1913 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Pollard, Percival (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - May 1 1905
        - Nov 13 1905
        - July 25 1907
        - Aug 30 1907
        - Apr 16 1908
        - Apr 27 1908
        - Feb 18 1909
        - Mar 7 1910
        - Sept 6 1910
        - Mar 30 1911
        - May 11 1911
        - Oct 21 1911
      - Read, Opie, Aug 15 1892 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Rearden, T.H. (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Jan 15 1892
        - Jan 29 1892
        - Feb 2 1892
        - Mar 2 1892
        - Mar 8 1892
        - Mar 14 1892
        - n.d.
        - n.d.
      - Redlich, Else (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Apr 26 1908
        - Dec 15 1908
        - Dec 21 1909
        - Dec 23 1910
        - Aug 9 1910
      - Rix, Alice, Nov 25 1899 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Roberts, Maud A. (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Apr 27 1908
        - June 16 1913
        - July 6 1913
        - Sept 19 1913
      - Robertson, Ruth, Apr 16 1911 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Root, Frederick Stanley, Nov 25 1899 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Sampson, Julia, Jan 18 1875 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Sargent, H.H. (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Sept [25?] 1898
        - Apr 29 1900
        - Nov 22 1906
        - Dec 5 1911
      - Savage, R.H., Oct 30 [1897] (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Scheffauer, Herman (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - May 31 1904
        - Aug 5 1904
        - Aug 11 1904
        - Sept 2 1904
        - Sept 17 1904
        - Oct 5 1904
        - Nov 9 1904
        - Nov 18 1904
        - Jan 8 1905
        - Jan 28 1905
        - Feb 22 1905
        - Mar 16 1905
        - Apr 8 1905
        - Apr 17 1905
        - Apr 18-27 1905
        - Apr 29 1905
        - Apr 30 1905
        - May 6 1905
        - May 9 1905
        - May 12 1905
        - May 12 1905
        - Aug 15 1905
      - Schenk, Margaret, May 17 1899 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Schulte, F.J. (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - May 20 1892
        - June 6 1892
        - June 28 1892
        - July 14 1892
        - Aug 4 1892
        - Aug 15 1892
        - Sept 10 1892
        - Sept 24 1892
        - Sept 28 1892
        - Oct 15 1892
        - Nov 11 1892
        - Nov 12 1892
        - Nov 19 1892
        - Dec 8 1892
        - Dec 9 1892
        - Jan 13 1893
        - [Feb?] 13 1893
        - Feb 23 1893
        - Sept 12 1893
        - Oct 7 1903
      - Shearer, Flora Mc.D. (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - Feb 11 1888
        - Nov 16 1897, [transcription]
        - Dec 11 1897, [transcription]
        - Dec 19 1897, [transcription]
      - Sherwood, H.H., Feb 6 1896 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Sickler, Nellie Vore (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - [ca Aug] [1913]
        - Sept 15 1913
      - Sinclair, Upton, March 8 1911 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Smith, R.S., July 3 1880 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Smith, Mrs. Ralph Sidney, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Somers, F.M. (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - Oct 13 n.y.
        - Nov 18 n.y.
      - Stedman, Edmund C., Mar 30 1901 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Stedman, Laura (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - Jan 12 1909
        - Jan 23 1909
      - Steele, E.L.G. (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - Apr 26 1873
        - Jan 2 1892
        - [Feb ?] 3 1892
        - Mar 25 1892
        - Mar 28 1892
        - Apr 14 1892
        - May 22 1892
        - Dec 1 1892
        - Dec 13 1892
        - Apr 13 1893
        - Apr 17 1893
        - Apr 21 1893
        - May 6 1893
        - June 24 1893
        - [ca. Mar] [1894], [on Verso of TLS by J.C. McCormick, Jr.]
        - Apr 27 1894
      - Sterling, George, Dec 25 1903 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Stoddard, C.W. (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - June ? 1874
        - Jun 1 1875
      - Stoddard, [L?] M., Sept 30 1891 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Syle, Louis DuPont (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - Nov 9 1899
        - Mar 7 1902
        - Jun 10 1902
        - Jun 14 1902
      - Temple, A.D., Apr 7 1909 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Thomas, Herbert, Nov 19 1909 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Thompson, Will H., Jun 15 1906 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Tilton, Ralph, Jul 3 1906 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Townsend, Annie Lake, Apr 6 1892 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Truesdell, A.W., Jan 15 1912 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Turner, [D?] W., Apr 19 1893 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Wagner, Madge Morris (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - Aug [27?] 1900
        - Sept 29 1900
      - Utassey, George von, Mar 5 1909, [AB's hand on verso] (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Van Antwerp, J.S. (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - Apr 16 [1896]
        - Apr 16 1896
      - Walker, James Randolph, Aug 21 1906 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Waterhouse, A,.D., Mar 24 1899 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Watkins, Charlie, Aug 19 1875 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Watkins, James T., [with transcriptions] (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - May 24 1873
        - Mar 2 1874
        - Mar 6 1874
        - Mar 22 1874
        - Jul 23 1874
        - Sept 9 1881
        - Jul 7 1888
        - Sept 9 [1889?]
        - Oct 23 1889
        - Oct 17 1890
        - Feb 15 1891
        - Feb 27 1891
        - Mar 5 1892
        - Aug 16 1892
        - n.d.
      - White, Geo. W., Feb 2 1911 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - White, Richard E., Sept 7 1913 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Whitehall, Alex, Dec 13 1903
      - Whymper, Fred (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - Apr 6 [1875]
        - Apr 19 1875
        - Dec 5 1875
      - Wilkinson, Warring (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - Jul 19 1895
        - Sept 23 1895
        - Sept 25 1895
      - Williams, Charles, Nov 26 1874 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Williams, T.T. (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - Jan 31 1896
        - Feb [?] 1896
        - Feb [?] 1896
        - Feb 3 1896
        - Feb 4 1896
        - Feb 15 1896
        - Feb 17 1896, [transcription]
        - Feb 24 1896
        - Mar 6 1896
        - Mar 7 1896, [incomplete; transcription of 1 & 2, .3]
        - Mar 11 1896
        - Mar 13 1896
        - Mar 14 1896
        - Mar 30 1896
        - Apr 30 1896
        - May 5 1896
        - May 5 1896
        - May 13 [1896]
        - May 26 1896
        - Jul 1 1896
        - May 23 1899
        - Jun 24 1901
        - Jul 2 1903
        - Apr 6 1905
        - May 1 1906
        - 2 T.T. Williams fragments
      - Wilmot, O.T. [Mrs.], Aug 20 1871 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Wilson, J. Crawford, Apr 19 1875 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Wolfson, Jos. (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - May 19 1901
        - Sept 22 1909
        - Nov 15 1910
      - Young, Rida Johnson, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Bierce, Helen w/env. To Dawson, Mr., Nov 22 1933 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Bierce, Leigh To Bierce, Helen, Jan 20 1897 (Box 2, Folder 6)